Guide to the Propaganda Poster Collection 1914-1996
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 5: French Posters
  - Subseries 5.2: French Post-World War II, 1943-1955
    - Meeting de la Jeunesse Intellectuelle, 1945; French; 61 x 85. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Friends of "Present Time." (Folder 73, Item 419)
      Poster directed toward students, announcing a meeting of young intellectuals organized by the Friends of "Present Time.
    - Parti de Renovation Republicaine, 1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. Yellow background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Vilers. (Folder 73, Item 420)
      Propaganda poster publicizing to the public the motto and goals of the Renovation Republican Party.
    - Soiree de Gala, 1945; French; 80 x 60 cm. (each part). White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: National Federation of Centers of Support for Workers and Deported Families. (Folder 73, Item 421)
      Poster announcing an evening event for the benefit of the Mutual Aid Centre. Split between two sheets of paper. Two copies of top portion of the poster.
    - Mamans! Femmes Parisiennes! Venez en Masse au Grand Rassemblement, 1945; French; 65 x 100 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Union of French Women. (Folder 73, Item 422)
      Directed toward the mothers and women of Paris, with the intention of encouraging them to attend a grand meeting.
    - Alerte a la Population Alerte aux Pouvoirs Publics: les Prisonniers de Guerre Reviennent, circa 1945-1955; French; 56 x 90 cm. White background with red text.; Creator/Publisher: Association of Prisoners of War of Seine. (Folder 73, Item 423)
      Seine poster alerting the public that prisoners of war are returning and what can be done for them.
    - Appel aux Francaises: Unis pour l'Effort Supreme de Guerre, 1945; French; 55.5 x 76 cm. White background and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Entreprise Parisienne de Presse et d'Imprimerie. (Folder 73, Item 424)
      An appeal to French men and women about the war effort, including a list of movements.
    - Commemoration, circa 1945-1955; French; 56 x 89 cm. White background with red and black text.; Creator/Publisher: Italian Socialist Party and Italian Action Party. (Folder 74, Item 425)
      A notice for a commemoration held by the Italian Committee of National Liberation, the Accession of the Italian League of Human Rights, the Communist Party, the Christian Democrat party, and the Liberal party.
    - Commemoration, circa 1945-1955; French; 56 x 90 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Italian Committee of National Liberation. (Folder 74, Item 426)
      Poster announcing a commemoration held by the Italian Socialist Party, the Italian Action Party, the Italian Communists in France, the Democrat Chretien Party, and the Liberal Party.
    - Employes des H.C.R.B. et Cantines Assistez tous aux Grands Meetings, 1945; French; 86.5 x 59.5 cm. (each part). White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Gomel-Pottier. (Folder 74, Item 427)
      Information about a grand meeting organized by the Union of Employees of Hotels, Cafes, Restaurants, Broths, and Canteens in the Paris Region. Lining the left side of the poster are eight photographs of men who are labeled as activists who paid with thei
    - Auschwitz, Buchenwald, Ravensbruck des Deportes vous Parlent Grand Meeting: pour le Chatiment des Traitres tous en Masse a Japy!, 1945; French; 85.5 x 62 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Speciale de l'A. N. V. N. (Folder 74, Item 428)
      A grand meeting held by the National Association of Victims of Nazism, the Secours Populaire de France, the French Assistance, and the National Movement Against Racism. The names of the three concentration camps are separated from the text with the outli
    - Commemoration du 12 Fevrier 1934 Victoire de la Republique sur le Fascisme: Toute la population Parisienne au Defile Devant la Statue de la Republique, 1945; French; 100 x 74 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 74, Item 429)
      A parade at the Statue of the Republic in commemoration of the February 12, 1934 fascist victory.
    - Nationalisation sans Delai du Trust du Gaz et de l'Electricite, circa 1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. White background with brown text.; Creator/Publisher: The National Federation of Lighting and Driving Forces. (Folder 74, Item 430)
      Propaganda poster encouraging the public's trust in gas and electricity.
    - Grand Gala au Profit des Ex-Prisonniers Sovietiques, circa 1945-1955; French; 62 x 100 cm. Green background with black text and graphic.; Creator/Publisher: Henry. (Folder 74, Item 431)
      French poster publicizing a grand gala consisting of singing, dancing, and orchestra playing to benefit former Soviet prisoners. Located in the bottom center of the poster is a graphic of a performance by Ann Laury and Jean Guien.
    - Parti de Renovation Republicaine, circa 1945; French; 62 x 85 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Chaffiotte. (Folder 75, Item 432)
      Public announcement of a new party, the Renovation Republican Party (P.R.R..), and an explanation of the party's program.
    - Rassemblement Antifasciste et Republicain: contre les Trusts et Leurs Agents les Factieux pour la Republique et l'Application du Programme du C.N.R., 1945; French; 111 x 38 cm. White background with red text.; Creator/Publisher: Speciale de l'Union des Syndicats. (Folder 75, Item 433)
      Propaganda poster featuring information about an Antifascist and Republican gathering, inviting all who identify with the Bastille Nation.
    - La Mort pour Petain l'Hitlerien, 1945; French; 60 x 80 cm. Black and white with red title.; Creator/Publisher: Speciale de l'A. N. V. N. (Folder 75, Item 434)
      Propaganda poster portraying a photograph of Philippe Petain and Adolf Hitler shaking hands, and an image of a ditch filled with dead bodies next to text explaining that the cost of that handshake was human lives.
    - Maurice Thorez: tous au Parc des Princes, circa 1945-1947; French; 100 x 33 cm. White background with red and black text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 75, Item 435)
      Poster with a graphic in the far left portion of Maurice Thorez, French Politian who served as vice premier of France.
    - Le 18 Mars 1871 Paris se Dressait contre la Capitulation!, 1945; French; 79.5 x 112.5 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 75, Item 436)
      A notice of the 74th anniversary of the Paris Commune under Maurice Thorez and Jacques Duclos.
    - Cinq Martyrs: Cinq Heros de la Classe Ouvriere et de l'Intelligence Francaise, circa 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 75, Item 437)
      A commemoration of five men who died for France, Georges Politzer, Jacques Solomon, Jacques Decour, Felix Cadras, and Arthur Dalidet.
    - Les Prisonniers et Deportes veulent le Chatiment des Responsables de la Defaite des Agents de la Trahison: le Droit de Vivre et de Travailler, ils Assisteront en Masse au Grand Meeting Organise par le Parti Communiste Francais, 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 75, Item 438)
      French poster publicizing a grand meeting of prisoners and deportees organized by the French Communist Party, in which Georgette Cadras and Andre Marty are speakers.
    - Le Scandale du Pain, 1945; French; 85 x 124 cm. Pink background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Pigalle. (Folder 76, Item 439)
      Encourages housewives, mothers, manual workers, and intellectuals to acknowledge the poor quality and insufficient rations of bread by attending a grand meeting organized by the National Federation of Food Workers, Hotels, Cafes, and Restaurants.
    - Dimanche 18 Fevrier 1945 au Bois de Vincennes (arriveees, passage Piste municipal): VIIIe Grand Cross de l'Humanite, French; 78.5 x 118.5 cm. White background with blue text and graphic.; Creator/Publisher: Sports and Gymnastics Federation of Labor. (Folder 76, Item 440)
      An announcement about the eighth Grand Cross of Humanity event. Includes an image of two men running, each with a number attached to their front.
    - Pour Hater la Fin Victorieuse de la Guerre, Reconstruire la France, Adherez au Parti de, 1945; French; 80 x 120 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 76, Item 441)
      Propaganda poster featuring five photographs placed diagonally of Maurice Thorez, Jacques Duclos, Marcel Cachin, Andre Marty, and Benoit Frachon. Additionally, the poster is split into three diagonal sections that are red, white, and blue.
    - Peuple de Paris sois Present aux Obseques Solennelles de Pierre Semard qui Auront lieu le Samedi 10 Mars 1945, French; 80.5 x 119.5 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 76, Item 442)
      Poster announcing the funeral of Pierre Semard. Above a photograph of Semard in the upper middle portion of the poster, he is described as an activist, patriot, and great Frenchman. There are two stripes in the upper right-hand corner, one red and the ot
    - 1er Mai 1945: Une Journee Chomee de Manifestations Republicaines et Antifascistes, French; 80 x 120 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Saint-Denis. (Folder 76, Item 443)
      Calls the attention of French workers to the goal of gaining an independent and prosperous France.. Symbols in the top corners consist of two circles with the text, Confederation Generale du Travail: Bien-etre-et-Liberte, and the image of two hands shakin
    - Un Bon de Solidarite: ne se Refuse pas!, circa 1941-1955; French; 45 x 15 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: ORAFF. (Folder 76, Item 444)
      Depicts a bill worth five French francs
    - Emplacement des Camps de Prisonniers de Guerre en Allemagne, circa 1945-1960; 76 x 54 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 76, Item 445)
      Features a map identifying prisoner of war camps located in Germany, Poland, and Russia (U.S.S.R.). Includes a legend and list of the camps.
    - Representation Theatrale, circa 1939-1950; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L'Emancipatrice (Folder 77, Item 446)
      Invitation to all families of prisoners and repatriated prisoners from Nogent-sur-Marne to a theatrical event.
    - Mairie du VIe Arrondissement, 1945; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Administrative Centrale. (Folder 77, Item 447)
      Poster regarding the Sixth Arrondissement of Paris.
    - Universitaires Prisonniers et Deportes: la Maison de l'Universite, circa 1940-1955; French; 78.5 x 30.5 cm. Yellow background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Sauvard. (Folder 77, Item 448)
      French poster directed toward prisoners and deportees from the University.
    - Le Laicisme contre l'Unite Francaise: Grande Reunion Publique, circa 1940-1955; French; 59 x 80 cm. White background with red-brown text.; Creator/Publisher: Mauvais. (Folder 77, Item 449)
      Publicizing a grand public meeting held in the Palais de la Mutualite, concerning secularism in France.
    - L'Aurore, circa 1940-1950; French; 59.5 x 79 cm. White background with red and black text.; Creator/Publisher: Jean-Goujon. (Folder 77, Item 450)
      Propaganda poster discussing the Republicans of France and events dating from July 10, 1940 and October 17, 1944.
    - Paris Veut Manger...Le Scandale du Marche noir doit Cesser!, circa 1944-1950; French; 59.5 x 79 cm. Pink background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: L. Hannequin. (Folder 77, Item 451)
      Propaganda poster exclaiming that the black market scandal must come to an end because it is starving the people of Paris.
    - Grand Gala, circa 1945-1955; French; 60 x 80 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Women of the Socialist Federation of the Seine. (Folder 77, Item 452)
      Announcement of a grand gala held in the Grand Amphitheatre de la Sorbonne for the benefit of the Commune martyre de Frevent (Pas-de-Calais) sinistree.
    - Epuration au sein du F.N., circa 1940-1955; French; 60 x 80 cm. White background with red text.; Creator/Publisher: Entreprise Parisienne de Presse et d'Imprimerie. (Folder 78, Item 453)
      List of three reminders from the National Front.
    - Grande Soiree de Gala, 1945; French; 56 x 76 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Local Committee of Liberation of the Sixth Arrondissement. (Folder 78, Item 454)
      Poster publicizing a grand gala organized by the Union of French Women of the Sixth District under the patronage of Madame Mallet.
    - A la Population Parisienne!, circa 1945-1955; 54 x 76 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: The Bureau of the Section of the Seine from the National Union of Teachers. (Folder 78, Item 455)
      A notice directed toward the population of Paris discussing schools and the need to defend education.
    - Grande Reunion: Les Etudiants et la Renaissance Francaise, 1945; French; 54.5 x 75.5 cm. White background with green text.; Creator/Publisher: Student National Front. (Folder 78, Item 456)
      A grand reunion of students involved in the Front National Etudiant at the Salle des Fetes.
    - Le VIe ARRt Adopte Conde-sur-Noireau, circa 1944-1955; French; 63.5 x 49 cm. (two parts); 61.5 x 49 cm. (two parts).; Creator/Publisher: Jacques MARX. (Folder 78, Item 457)
      White background with brown and green text, and red images. Features photographs of the destruction of La Mairie, La rue Saint-Martin, La Place principale (Place Dumont-d'Urville), La Rue principale, and L'Eglise Saint-Sauveur. Additionally, depicts an i
    - Engagez-vous, Rengagez-vous dans L'Armee Francaise de L'Armistice, circa 1940-1955; French; 48 x 21 cm. White background with red, blue, and black text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 78, Item 458)
      Encourages men to join the French Army of Armistice. Includes two graphics of patriotic labrys decorated with stars and the colors red, white, and, blue.
    - Les Elections Approchent, mais, circa 1945; French; 49.5 x 65 cm. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Association of Prisoners of the War Department of the Seine. (Folder 78, Item 459)
      Announcement from the Association of Prisoners of War Department of the Seine about an approaching election.
    - Comite Local de Liberation du VIe: Etats Generaux de la Renaisssance Francaise, circa 1940-1955; French; 39.5 x 60.5 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: Local Committee of the Sixth Liberation. (Folder 79, Item 460)
      Features text, including a short list under the heading Avez-vous Pense? In the upper left-hand corner are red and blue stripes.
    - Servir: Federation des Jeunesses Communistes de France XIe Congres National: Paris Paques 1945, French; 40 x 60 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Federation of Young Communists of France. (Folder 79, Item 461)
      French poster portraying two young men, one dressed as a laborer, the other a soldier. Marching next to the men is a young woman dressed professionally.
    - Femmes c'est a vous que s'Adressera, circa 1940-1955; French; 85.5 x 33 cm. Gray background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Communist Party. (Folder 79, Item 462)
      Poster directed toward the women of France, publicizing the appearance of Maurice Thorez, Secretary General of the French Communist Party.
    - Francaises!, circa 1940-1955; French; 50 x 61 cm. Light blue background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: French Communist Party. (Folder 79, Item 463)
      Propaganda poster dedicated to text, including the insistence of a gathering for the crushing of Fascism, for Democracy, for the Republic, and for France. Includes a symbol in the upper right-hand corner of a helmet detailed with a blue circle within a r
    - [German and French Notice from the Der Feldkommandant], circa 1943-1955; German; French; 65 x 49.5 cm. Yellow background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Saint-Cloud. (Folder 79, Item 464)
      A public notice, written in both German and French, discussing workers leaving the sites of the Todt Organization.
    - Aux Habitants du VIe Arrond, circa 1945-1955; French; 50 x 64.5 cm. Yellow background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Administrative Centrale. (Folder 79, Item 465)
      French poster directed toward the habitants of the sixteenth administrative district of Paris.
    - Un Deuxieme Camion de Colis pour nos Soldats est Parti le Samedi 31 Mars 1945 pour le Front de la Rochelle, French; 50 x 65 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Administrative Centrale. (Folder 79, Item 466)
      Notice of a truck of packages leaving for the front of La Rochelle. Includes a list of contributors and the amount of parcels gifted to soldiers.
    - "La Nation en Marche", 1945; French; 49.5 x 65.5 cm. White background with black and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Curial-Archeraud II. (Folder 80, Item 467)
      Showing of the "La Nation en Marche" in the Paris concert hall, Salle Pleyel. Consists of an original sheet with a longer piece pasted at the top of the poster providing the location and time of the event.
    - Vous etes Responsable de la Reussite de la Campagne en Faveur de notre Filleule Sinistree Conde-sur-Noireau (Calvados), circa 1945-1955; French; 48.5 x 64 cm. Pink background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Jacques MARX. (Folder 80, Item 468)
      French poster consisting of a list of dates and the corresponding information for the campaign of "Amitie et Solidarite" ("Friendship and Solidarity").
    - Preparation Militaire, circa 1940-1955; French; 40 x 59 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Watelet-Arbelot. (Folder 80, Item 469)
      Poster presented by the Local Committee of Liberation of the 6th District and the United Forces of the Patriotic Youth, describing military preparations. Two French flags are crossed in the middle of the upper portion of the poster. The backside features
    - Que Faire de l'Allemagne?: Grand Debat de Politique Exterieure, circa 1945-1955; French; 40 x 59.5 cm. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Commerce et des Postes. (Folder 80, Item 470)
      Public notice of a great discussion of foreign policy regarding Germany held at the Salle Pleyel in Rue Saint-Honore.
    - Recuperation de la Laine, circa 1945-1955; French; 40 x 60 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Administrative Centrale. (Folder 80, Item 471)
      An appeal to the French women of the sixth district of Paris regarding the recovery of wool.
    - Le Laicisme contre l'Unite Francaise, 1945; French; 40 x 56 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: P. Vaillant. (Folder 80, Item 472)
      Propaganda poster making an appeal against secularism in France and announcing a grand public meeting at the Palace of Mutualite.
    - Cheres Amies, circa 1945-1955; French; 37.5 x 56 cm. Green background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: The Friends of the Front. (Folder 80, Item 473)
      Poster addressing the people of France, arguing that the war is not over.
    - Jeunes Gens de Classes Mobilisables Inscrivez-vous Immediatement a nos Cours de: Preparation Militaire, circa 1945-1955; French; 37 x 53.5 cm. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: A. Lapied. (Folder 81, Item 474)
      Encourages young men to register for the course titled, "Military Preparation."
    - Vous Viendrez tous Dimanche a la Kermesse Monstre du Jardin du Luxembourg en Faveur de la Ville Sinistree de Conde-sur-Noireau, circa 1945-1955; French; 29 x 39.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Jacques MARX. (Folder 81, Item 475)
      Poster announcing an event for the benefit of the ruined city, Conde-sur-Noireau. Listed below the title, the poster informs readers that there will be entertainment, good deals, and good action.
    - Journee Antillo-Guyanaise, 1945; French; 30 x 39.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: A. Tribet. (Folder 81, Item 476)
      Poster illustrating two men, one dark skinned, the other light skinned, joining hands as they raise their arms. The men are facing away from the viewers as they stand upon islands with the outline of France and the French colors in the background.
    - Parisiens, circa 1940-1955; French; 38.5 x 55.5 cm. White background with red text.; Creator/Publisher: The Anti-Fascist League. (Folder 81, Item 477)
      French poster dedicated to text. Directed toward the people of Paris from the Anti-Fascist League, discussing lieutenants Vallin and Barrachin.
    - Grande Conference Publique, circa 1945-1955; French; 31.5 x 50 cm. Blue background with black text.; Creator/Publisher: Union of Intellectuals. (Folder 81, Item 478)
      Notice about a grand public conference featuring Mr. Damalas, a Doctor in Law.
    - [Renovation Republican Party Candidates], 1945; French; 21 x 45 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: L. Hauguel. (Folder 81, Item 479)
      A list of candidates from the Renovation Republican Party for an upcoming election. Includes Petiteau Marcel, Varennes Marie-Jean, Desplats Jean, Soulie Andre, M. Dault, Delarbre Henri, Wargnier Pierre, Laurent Blanche, Guerin Eugene, Robinet Andre, Carc
    - Grande Quinzaine des Enfants de Fusilles et Deportes, circa 1945-1955; French; 27.5 x 44 cm. White background with red text.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 81, Item 480)
      Poster advertising an event for children from families affected by the war. Includes four boxes along the left side, listing important dates next to the explained attractions.
    - Parti de Renovation Republicaine, circa 1945-1955; French; 25 x 32.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: J. Chaffiotte. (Folder 82, Item 481)
      Depicts a list of the names of 14 individuals significant to the Renovation Republican Party; Jean Camp, Benjamin Graulle, Edouard Lassalle, Pierre Beauvais, Denise Favereau, Alexandre Thirion, Pierre Bauzou, Yves Chabrol, Suzanne de Parrel, Pierre Betei
    - Habitants du VIe, circa 1943-1955; French; 30 x 40 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Jacques MARX. (Folder 82, Item 482)
      French poster directed toward the habitants of the sixth Arrondissement of Paris from the C.L.L. (Comite Local de la Liberation du VIe Arrondissement).
    - Assemblee d'Information des etats Generaux de la Renaissance Francaise, circa 1945-1955; French; 28 x 40 cm. Black and white with red and blue accents.; Creator/Publisher: Henri Dieval. (Folder 82, Item 483)
      Announcement of an assembly providing information on the Renaissance in France. Features two diagonal strips running from the top right corner, to the bottom left corner. One is red, and the other is blue.
    - 2 Avril 1945 Journee de la Liberation de Paris: Un Drapeau a Chaque Fenetre, French; 40 x 18 cm. White background with red and blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Havas; Jombart. (Folder 82, Item 484)
      Propaganda poster informing viewers to place a flag in their windows on the Day of the Liberation of Paris, April 2, 1945.
    - Comite Local de Liberation du VIe Arrondissement, circa 1945-1955; French; 30 x 20 cm. White background with blue text.; Creator/Publisher: Jacques MARX. (Folder 82, Item 485)
      Notice from the C.L.L. (Comite Local de Liberation du VIe Arrondissement) about a unanimously adopted declaration.
    - Le 6e Arrondissement Adopte Conde-sur-Noireau (Calvados): Campagne "Amitie et Solidarite", 1945; French; 30 x 40 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Le Comite de Parrainage. (Folder 82, Item 486)